Guide to Voices of Crown Heights oral histories 2016.027
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Historical Society, 2016-2017; 2016.027.1
  - Cuthbert, Donna, 2017 August 25; 2016.027.1.23
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bars (Drinking establishments) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gay culture |z New York (State) |z New York; Gays |x Social life and customs; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Identity politics; Lesbians; Multiculturalism; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queer culture; Transgender people; Cuthbert, Donna; George W. Wingate High School; King, William (William "Butch" King); La'Viticus, Timothy; Starlite Lounge (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - de Zayas, Michael, 2017 March 17; 2016.027.1.08
    Forty-three at the time of the 2017 interview, Michael de Zayas is a business owner from the Miami, Florida area. His father is Cuban-born and his mother is a White woman from New York. He moved to New York in the 1990s, became a travel writer, and then a business owner; opening Neighborhoodies, which had stores across the country. After selling that business, moving to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and becoming a father for the first time, de Zayas opened the popular Little Zelda café. Several more businesses in the area followed, including Nagle's Bagels (also in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Prospect Lefferts Gardens neighborhoods of Brooklyn), Hullaballo Books, Two Saints, Jewel City Yoga, Simple Syrup, and Linden Salon. He had relocated to the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn after five years of living in Crown Heights.
    In this interview, Michael de Zayas begins with growing up in Miami and his journey to New York. He relates that he first moved to New York to attend graduate school at Sarah Lawrence College, where he received a master's degree in poetry. He became a travel writer and speaks about his experiences traveling, as well as his relationship to community while being a young man in New York City; mainly in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan. Major turning points discussed include: founding his Neighborhoodies business, becoming a father, moving to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and his business ventures there. He prides himself on constructing his businesses around the concept of "radical friendliness;" in order to counter much of the anti-social behavior that exists in coffee shops and other kinds of stores in New York City. He is committed to being part of and building community in Crown Heights. He is also trying to rethink how his businesses can better serve the needs of all community members, not just new arrivals, in the area. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Clothing trade |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); East Village (New York, N.Y.); Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Storefronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.); City University of New York. School of Law at Queens College; de Zayas, Michael; Little Zelda (Restaurant); Neighborhoodies, Inc. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Ellenbogen, Amy, 2016 July 21; 2016.027.1.01
    Born in the Bronx in 1973, Amy Ellenbogen grew up in White Plains in a Jewish family of Eastern European descent. She attended Columbia University, where she received both her Bachelor of Arts in Ethnic Studies and her Masters of Science in Social Work. Since 2002, she has been the director of the Crown Heights Community Mediation Center, developing and implementing programs as well as overseeing day-to-day operations. As director, she planned and directed the first New York State Cure Violence replication site, Save Our Streets Crown Heights, an anti-gun violence program that uses a public health approach. As of 2017, Ellenbogen is part of the planning team developing culturally competent trauma-informed programming for young men of color and Save Our Streets Bed-Stuy.*
    *Source: http://crownheights.org/staff/amy-ellenbogen/
    In this interview, Amy Ellenbogen describes the influences and events in her life that led up to her work at the Crown Heights Community Mediation Center, which she has led as director since 2002. She talks about the importance of her Marxist-leaning grandmother who self-identified as a "Jewish humanist atheist;" and asking questions of her parents at an early age about Jewish rituals and traditions. She recalls her first trip to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the mid-1980s as a guest of a Lubavitch Hasidic host family as part of a Jewish "in-reach" program that the Crown Heights-based orthodox Jewish community conducted. She reflects on coming of age in a diverse community and school, and her early questions about differences between her peers and herself were informed by racial and class dynamics. These questions would continue to shape her outlook, leading her to found ROOTED (Respecting Ourselves and Others Through EDucation) in graduate school. She traces the evolution of her work at the Mediation Center, from an organization founded after the August 1991 unrest to address inter-cultural conflict, to one that primarily provides neighborhood services, mediates landlord-tenant issues, and works to curb gun-related violence and killings through violence prevention and violence interruption programs. Finally, she reflects on the impact that gentrification has had on Crown Heights and the kind of work the Mediation Center does. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 21st century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish women; Jews, American |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism in mass media; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; White Plains (N.Y.); Bogan, Ken; Camara, Karim; Columbia University; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights Mediation Center; Ellenbogen, Amy; Golden, Howard; Norman, Clarence, Jr.; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
  - Green, Richard, 2016 October 18; 2016.027.1.02
    Richard Green was born in Tela, Honduras in 1948 and grew up in various locations in Brooklyn. He graduated from Erasmus Hall High School, served in the Marines, achieved an undergraduate degree at Marist College and attended a graduate program at the State University at New Paltz. Beginning in 1969, he was a permanent fixture of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and raised his children there. In 1978, Green founded the Crown Heights Youth Collective and he still served as the Chief Executive Officer as of 2016. He also co-founded the Street Outreach Program, has worked with five New York mayors as of 2016, and assisted with Project Cure, a community healing organization formed in the wake of the Crown Heights unrest of 1991. Since 1993, he has taught as an adjunct professor at Medgar Evers College. He has served on boards, as a trustee or a member, of several high-profile government and public services departments for New York City. Green has been heard on radio as a commentator and producer. He is a husband, father and grandfather. His wife, Myrah Brown Green, was interviewed for the Weeksville series of this collection.
    In this interview, Richard Green recalls his early childhood in Honduras and Texas before his family moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn around the time he was in sixth grade. He describes the kinds of recreational activities that were available to young people in the 1950s and early 1960s, including the informal games they played as well as more organized activities such as the Police Athletics League organized sports tournaments. He reflects on his political coming of age in the midst of the Civil Rights Movement, and being inspired by the Brooklyn activities of leaders like the Reverend Milton Galamison and Malcolm X. After graduating from high school, Green joined the United States Marine Corps, and he details some of the challenges he faced, being a Black man navigating the military at the height of the anti-war and Black Power movements. He talks about the changes in the neighborhood, which he noticed after completing his tour of duty and returning to Crown Heights in 1976. He recounts how these conditions—like building abandonment and truancy— inspired him to found the Crown Heights Youth Collective in 1978, and the work it has done over the past three decades to help organize tenants, address youth education, and respond to police-community tensions. Some of the high profile incidents he discusses include reactions to the police killing of Arthur Miller, the racially motivated killing of Michael Griffith, and the 1991 Crown Heights unrest. Green was also recorded for the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection in 2010 (2010.020). Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
    Assassination -- United States; Black Muslims; Black nationalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z New York; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Muslims |z New York (State) |z New York; Nostrand Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Peace movements |z United States |x History; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z New York; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Black Panther Party; Chisholm, Shirley; Crown Heights Youth Collective (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Daughtry, Herbert, 1931-; Erasmus Hall High School; Evers, Medgar Wiley, 1925-1963; Galamison, Milton A., 1923-1988 (Milton Arthur); Green, Richard; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Griffith, Michael, 1963-1986; Kennedy, John F., 1917-1963 (John Fitzgerald); Koch, Ed; Miller, Arthur, Jr.; United States Marine Corps; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965
  - Griffith, Mark Winston, 2017 July 18; 2016.027.1.19
    Mark Winston Griffith grew up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, as well as Queens, as a Black child of second generation Caribbean migrants. Born in 1963, he and his family moved from Crown Heights to Queens and he continued to visit Crown Heights regularly to visit his grandmother. He attended New York City public schools and a boarding school in New Jersey. After graduating from Brown University in 1985 he returned to Brooklyn, where he lived on Dean Street between Nostrand and New York Avenues, and has remained ever since, mainly as an activist and non-profit professional.
    In this first of two interviews, a recording error results in the oral history picking up the already-in-progress telling of Mark Winston Griffith's move to Queens from the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn as a child. Although he moved to Queens in the third grade, it was due to his grandmother remaining in Crown Heights that enabled him to spend a great deal of time in the neighborhood, and he describes the part of his childhood spent there. He also shares other biographical turns in his young adulthood. Having become politically active at Brown University, Griffith recalls his desire to return to Crown Heights to work for Al Vann, but instead found an opening with Assemblyman Clarence Norman, Jr. He remembers that work, as well as being a co-founder of CHANT (Crown Heights Africans Networking Together), a local activist group. Griffith briefly mentions his English Literature studies in Ghana, then talks about working for Community Service Society and the Crown Heights Neighborhood Improvement Association; both of which put him in a position to cofound the Central Brooklyn Partnership and the Brooklyn Cooperative Federal Credit Union. This interview ends abruptly, with Griffith discussing the growth and decline of the Credit Union. Interview conducted by Matthew Birkhold.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans -- Politics and government -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community banks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political participation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Social movements |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Cooperative Federal Credit Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brown University; Central Brooklyn Partnership (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Community Service Society of New York; Crown Heights Neighborhood Improvement Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Griffith, Mark Winston; Norman, Clarence, Jr.; Vann, Albert
  - Griffith, Mark Winston, 2017 July 27; 2016.027.1.20
    In this second of two interviews, Mark Winston Griffith begins by describing his first memories of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and the way in which the neighborhood's Black cultural and political institutions shaped his childhood and his future. Griffith then resumes his description of the Brooklyn Cooperative Federal Credit Union before discussing his career as a journalist, his run for city council in 2009-2010, and his role in founding Brooklyn Movement Center in 2012. He describes Brooklyn Movement Center as the culmination of his experiences in Crown Heights and the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Griffith then expresses his concern over gentrification. In closing, he considers what the future of Crown Heights might look like. Interview conducted by Matthew Birkhold.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans -- Politics and government -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community banks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political participation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Social movements |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Cooperative Federal Credit Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Movement Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Central Brooklyn Partnership (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Griffith, Mark Winston; Vann, Albert
  - Johnson, Albert, 2017 October 6; 2016.027.1.25
    Albert Johnson grew up in Cleveland, Ohio, where his mother worked for a major newspaper. Johnson attended Cleveland public schools, graduating from Glendale High School in 1965. He moved to New York in the late sixties, where he attended the Fashion Institute of Technology, and went on to work as a designer in production in the Garment District. In 1996, he was diagnosed with HIV and became sick, spending the next few years trying several treatments. He began working at the Starlite Lounge as a bartender on September the 10th, 2001, a day before the attack on the Twin Towers. The Starlite was one of the oldest city bars to welcome gay, as well as heterosexual, patrons. He worked at the bar in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn until it closed, August 9th, 2010.
    In the first session of this two session interview, Albert Johnson talks about growing up in Cleveland, Ohio in the nineteen fifties and sixties. He describes the African-American community and neighborhood he was reared by, and how unique and special an experience it was for him. He discusses the political climate and racial dynamics of this time and place by telling stories about his family, neighborhood, schoolmates, teachers, and household he grew up in. This session of the interview, conducted by Svetlana Kitto, ends abruptly.
    African Americans -- United States; Bars (Drinking establishments) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Business enterprises -- African Americans -- United States; Cleveland (Ohio); Community identity; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); Public Schools; Race relations |z United States; Racism in education; Restaurants; Riots -- United States; Television |z United States |y 20th century; Johnson, Albert; Starlite Lounge (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Johnson, Albert, 2017 October 22; 2016.027.1.26
    In the second session of a two session interview, Albert Johnson intersects his childhood story with another layer of complexity: growing up gay. He tells stories about his family's reactions to his sexuality, both surprising and sad. He enumerates and describes in detail all the gay clubs in Cleveland he went to as a young adult, including two different bars run by lesbians. He moves onto talk about his move to Buffalo, New York, where he worked at a hospital and met his first true love; John, a doctor. Together, they moved to New York City, where Johnson attended the Fashion Institute of Technology, then worked in the Garment District. He tells stories about the clubs he went to, the people he loved, and the fashion business circa the 1980s. He tells of the losses to AIDS in its early years in New York, including John. Johnson was diagnosed with HIV in 1996 and relates those early experiences of trying to get medical care and treatment. He talks about meeting "Butchie" King, who was a DJ at the Starlite Lounge in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and how it took some convincing for Johnson to come bartend there in 2001. He talks about attracting a regular clientele by being the first to make fancy mixed drinks at the bar; describing some drinks and some patrons. He compares various eras of ownership of the Starlite, and tells stories about the place and what it meant to the community. He reflects on the ways the Starlite Lounge changed his life and the meaning of it, and how once the people who made the Starlite what it was were dead and/or gone, it was time for it to end. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; AIDS (Disease) |z New York (State) |z New York; Bars (Drinking establishments) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Buffalo (N.Y.); Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cleveland (Ohio); Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gay culture |z New York (State) |z New York; Gays |x Social life and customs; HIV-positive persons |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Lesbians; Multiculturalism; New York (N.Y.); Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Presidents |z United States |x Election |y 2008; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Transgender people; Johnson, Albert; King, William (William "Butch" King); Obama, Barack; Starlite Lounge (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Johnson, Sophie, 2017 June 1; 2016.027.1.15
    An African American woman originally from Baltimore, Maryland, Sophie Williams Johnson was age eighty-two at the time of her 2017 interview. She had lived in Brooklyn for "about fifty years," most of that time spent in the Crown Heights neighborhood. A musician and retired arts administrator, she had also served as a board member and director of programming for the New Muse, on the community programs staff at Brooklyn Museum, and as Director of Magnolia Tree Earth Center. Among her many endeavors at the New Muse, she worked with "Where We At: Black Women Artists," a Black women's art collective.
    In the interview, Sophie Williams Johnson talks about growing up in Baltimore; including learning violin and becoming a musician, then meeting and marrying her husband. Of her time in Brooklyn, she recalls how she and her husband worked as musicians in churches, and organized their own youth music programs in the community. Johnson speaks about working at the New Muse cultural institution, Brooklyn Museum, and Magnolia Tree Earth Center, as well as her work with Community Board Nine and the Bergen Street Community Garden. She concludes with her observations on community change and the effects of gentrification in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Conditons Governing Access and Use
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baltimore (Md.); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Museums |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Museum; Community Board No. 9 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Historic First Church of God in Christ (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Johnson, Sophie Williams; Magnolia Tree Earth Center of Bedford-Stuyvesant, Inc. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muse Community Museum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Juravich, Nick, 2017 May 18; 2016.027.1.13